Jean Ritchie and George Pickow collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 4: Moving images
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1172, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean Ritchie Concert/Camera #1/Set 1/Brasstown/Raw Footage 3 /1/60
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1173, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean Interview I
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1174, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean Interview Tape III
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1175, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Black Waters Master/Jean Jon Peter Sing and Play for Japan Victor
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1176, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    New Master/Stiroff with intro
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1177, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    New Stiroff Master/11/11/1986/23:04
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1178, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Stiroff Intro and Song/R-1
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1179, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Stir-Off/Producer: George Pickow/____ dupe was better
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1180, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    "See Hear"/Issue 2/Bars 1:00/Black 1:00/Video 55:38/Mixed audio on Channels 1 and 2
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1181, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Good Morning Freedom
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1182, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Folklife Videos Sample Master/Folklife Video Sampler
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1183, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1184, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    "See Hear"/3/4 Master
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1185, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    "See Hear"/Promo/Master /Length 6:26 /Audio-mixed track on Ch 1 and 2
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1186, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Ballads/Blues/Bluegrass/Master/good/36 minutes /NBC/"Blues and Blue Grass"/B-Roll/2-2-1989/Footage of Alan Lomax/Clarence Ashley and Doc Watson
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1187, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Old Bangum 7:50/Homer the Horse 8:56 /9/20/85
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1188, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean Sings Old Bangum/Camera #2 /orig /second Tru
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1189, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jeff and Jeff/3 Screens/Concert/#3 /3 camera angles
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1190, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jeff and Jeff/Concert 3/Right Camera
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1191, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jeff and Jeff/Edit Master/Title 5:08 /Doodle Bug 8:20 /Toota Woofa 30:20 /Chicken 38:47
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1192, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jeff and Jeff/Right Camera/Concert 2
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1193, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Oscar Brand at Jewish Arts Festival/#1/Oscar Brand with John Foley at the International Jewish Arts Festival/1992/Long Island, New York
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1194, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Oscar talking about Jean and City Buildings
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1195, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog.
    1) Corn Husk Dolls/Folkways/Toys from the Fie... dub of TC7203 /Ep1 30:00; 2) Great American Music Company /Battle
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1196, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean Richie at SCC/BandW/1/18/1978 /Copy 1 /1 of 2
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1197, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean Richie at SCC 1/18/1978/Copy #1 /2 of 2 /BandW
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1198, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Hillbilly Film/Good /Hillbilly dub best
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1199, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean Library Concert/1997/Part II
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1200, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean at Westminster College/Salt Lake City/Utah /do not use /covers off on heads
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1201, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean Ritchie/Kentucky Homecoming Festival/Bardstown, Kentucky/June 1, 1996
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1202, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Chapter Presidents 1:00:00 to 6:10:01 video /to 6:14:27 audio/audio same both ch. /running time 5:10:01 - video /Lee-Yellow-Submarine/Master/11:30 Jean-Black Waters Master
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1203, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Black Waters/Raw Footage/Dub
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1204, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Oss Oss Wee Oss/Master edit /23:16 (recording time) /12/17/86
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1205, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Square Dance and Play Party/Dub
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1206, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Sweet Rivers and Black Waters
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1207, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Mountain Born/The Jean Ritchie Story/Preliminary Cut first 20:00
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1208, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Black Waters at 5:30/New Concert/Slides for edit /raw slide show for edit
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1209, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Oss Oss Safety
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1210, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Mountain Born: The Jean Ritchie Story
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1211, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Work Tape #1/Treasurer's Report Book /No sound? footage not found in Blues Ballads and ____
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1212, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Ballads Blues and Bluegrass!/Homemade version/not too sharp
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1213, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Lyrics and Legends/"Sea Songs"/1997 Dub
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1214, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Mexican-American/Border Songs/Lyrics and Legends/Sea Shantys/Jean and Edna on porch/Roscoe Holcomb/Ed McCurdy
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1215, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Material for Street Show Intro
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1216, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Peter Kennedy and Jean Intro/Street Show/new 16mm Camera Shot
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1217, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Backgrounds/Jean Ritchie/4/7/92
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1218, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Ireland Raw
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1219, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Peter Kennedy/Video Magazine Interview/Part I
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1220, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Peter Kennedy/Video Magazine Interview/Part II
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1221, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Peter Kennedy
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1222, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Peter Kennedy and Jean Intro/Streetshow/Oss Oss Wee Oss /2
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1223, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Final Irish Kitchen/(2x)/and Kennedy/Irish Kitchens
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1224, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Peter Kennedy/Streetshow/Unedited/#2
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1225, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Peter Kennedy/Street Rituals/Street show/unedited/raw footage/#3
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1226, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Rainbow Quest/#5/Peter Seeger/Jean Ritchie/Bernice Reagon/Clearwater Publishing Company, Inc.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1227, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Streetshow safety/#1/NTSC/stereo/color/Nov. 1988/11 minutes
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1228, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Peter Kennedy Streetshow/Unedited/#1
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1229, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    "Part of Our Heritage"/master/Hindman School slide show/also camera work for earthquakes
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1230, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean Documentary Master
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1231, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Ramblin' [series title]/Jean Ritchie [program title]/Keith Newman [producer]/Athens, Ohio/9/23/80 /58:30 /color /2-channel
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1232, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Wide Wide World Christmas/'88 music
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1233, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    "Too Many Shadows"/safety
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1234, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Winter Grace/master
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1235, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Lomax's house/original footage from Ballads Blues and Bluegrass/Good quality pics of Clarence Ashley, Doc Watson, Jean Ritchie, Pete LaFarge/shot of Ramblin Jack/no sound
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1236, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Jean talks on Aran
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1237, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Music and Images from the North/mixed audio on channel 1 and 2/color bars 1:01 /black 0:58 /video 5:43
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1238, December 13, 1971, 1 videoreel (90 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, black and white; 5 in. 1/2 in. (width).
    Jean Ritchie Performs at Cooperative Homemakers Council Christmas Party/Part I/Port Washington. Unedited.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1239, December 13, 1971, 1 videoreel (90 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, black and white; 5 in. 1/2 in. (width).
    Jean Ritchie Performs at Cooperative Homemakers Council Christmas Party/Part II. Unedited.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1240, March 17, 1972, 1 videoreel (90 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, black and white; 5 in. 1/2 in. (width).
    Jean Ritchie/Port Washington, New York/Public Library VTR Project/March 17, 1972 Part 1/Credits: Project director and interviewer, Walter Dale; camera people, Patricia Deitch, Gabrielle Ember. Summary: Native Kentucky mountains' folk singer, now a Port Washington resident, in informal interview and performance with her family. VTR-13. Unedited.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1241, March 17, 1972, 1 videoreel (90 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, black and white; 5 in. 1/2 in. (width).
    Jean Ritchie/Port Washington, New York/Public Library VTR Project/March 17, 1972/Part 2. VTR-14. Unedited. See summary for MV1240.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1242, March 17, 1972, 1 videoreel (90 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, black and white; 5 in. 1/2 in. (width).
    Jean Ritchie/Port Washington, New York/Public Library VTR Project/March 17, 1972/Part 3. VTR-15. Unedited. See summary for MV1240.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1243, 1 videocassette (VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    Ramona Jones and family, and Jean Ritchie.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1244, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog.
    Martha Connerton Dance Group with Jean Ritchie.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1245, 1 videocassette (S-VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    Jean at Hindman.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1246, 1 videocassette (VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    Library Concert.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1247, 1 videocassette (VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    Blood and Orchids; 20/20 Labor Union and Factories; shots
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1248, 1 videocassette (VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    Patchwork /blues /Lomax
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1249, 1 videocassette (VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    American Patchwork; Appalachian Journey - Lomax
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1250, 1 videocassette (VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    Jean Ritchie and John McCutcheon; Elkins, Virginia.
    - Jean Ritchie and John McCutcheon; Elkins, Virginia
      - Amazing Grace
      - Mountain Born
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1251, 1 videocassette (VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    Carnegie Hall Christmas concert.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1252, 1 videocassette (VHS; 30 min.): analog.
    Kentucky Play Party and Square Dance. Filmed in Jean Ritchie's community. Lyrics and Legends, NET TV series.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1253, 1984, 1 videocassette (VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    Portrait of America: Kentucky. Turner Broadcasting, 1984.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1254, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog.
    Walk in woods.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1255, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog.
    Caffé Lena tribute.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1256, 1 videocassette (VHS; 120 min.): analog.
    Jean singing with dulcimer, Kentucky. Hadassah Hospital. LP - for Oscar [Brand]. Woman in White 5/16.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1257, 1964, 1 videocassette (Betacam SP; 3 min.): digital.
    Jean Ritchie at the Newport Folk Festival
    - Blood on Your Shirt Sleeve
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1258, 1964, 1 videocassette (Betacam SP; 3 min. 41 sec.): digital.
    - Old King Quine
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1259, 1 videocassette (U-matic; 30 min.): analog.
    Winter Grace. Safety copy.
  - AFC 2008/005: MV1260, 1 videocassette (U-matic): analog.
    Black Waters. For Japanese Victor. Safety copy.
- Series 5: Artifacts
  - Appalachian dulcimer, 1923 (Box 219)
    A dulcimer made in 1923 by J. Edward Thomas of Knott County, Kentucky. Possibly walnut; three-string, half-fretted, with four heart-shaped soundholes. The shape and the soundholes are the "Kentucky style," developed by Thomas. It can be seen in photos of Jean with a gathering of her dulcimers, and on the cover of her album "The Most Dulcimer." It appears near the bottom edge of the cover, and can be only partially seen.
  - Dulcimer pick, circa 1970s (Box 220)
    An asymetrical piece of yellow plastic, cut from the top of a Mazola margarine container. It was Jean's pick of choice.
  - Bowman Patterson Award, undated (Box 220)
    Bowman Patterson Award, from the University of Kentucky; given to Jean in a personalized presentation case. A medallion embedded in a clear Lucite block.
  - Lanyards, circa 1960s-2000s (Box 221)
    Lanyards, most with cords or ribbons still attached, for Jean and George to wear at concerts, festivals, and other events. Most are for Jean. Those for George are usually as a guest or as a photographer.
  - Buttons and badges, circa 1960s-2000s (Box 220)
    Most serve the same function as lanyards: as identification for Jean or George at events. Some buttons have a saying or slogan, and are not intended as identification.
  - Banner, 2005 (Box 218)
    Banner for the musical, "Singin' the Moon Up: the Voice of Jean Ritchie." Only "Sing [sic] the Moon Up" and the performance dates appear on the banner. Blue letters on a yellow background. 16 in. x 30 in.
  - Two decorative paper napkins, circa 1950s (Box 220)
    The first napkin shows a man and woman dancing; the border is edged on two sides with depictions of clover. The illustrations are in black and shades of green. The second napkin has a bicentennial theme, in red white, and blue, with stars, the Liberty bell, and a striped border cut to resemble fringe.